Finding Aid to the Martha Tolles papers SSC.MS.00755
Sophia Smith Collection
Martha Tolles papers
1965-2015
Sophia Smith Collection
Tolles, Martha
SSC.MS.00755
3.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
Martha Tolles is a Smith College graduate and author of numerous works of popular childrens' fiction, including the "Darci" and "Katie" series of books, which were published in the 1980s. This collection of her papers documents her writing through drafts, correspondence with her editors and fans, and publicity materials, including interviews conducted with Tolles.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections. This collection has not been organized or processed beyond its initial accessioning.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated by Martha Tolles in 2015.
Biographical Note
Martha Tolles is a Smith College graduate and author of numerous works of popular childrens' fiction, including the "Darci" and "Katie" series of books, which were published in the 1980s.
Born in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, the daughter of Natalie Dunbar and Willis Gregory, Martha Tolles grew up in Rye, New York. She graduated from Smith College in 1943 with a degree in English. While at Smith, Tolles served as a reporter and then assistant editor for the college newspaper,"The SCAN" and was a member of the College Radio Board. After college, she worked as a reporter for"Port Chester Daily Item." Shortly after graduation, Martha Gregory married E. Leroy Tolles, founder of the prominent law firm Munger, Tolles and Olson, based in Los Angeles. Together, the couple had six children and were married sixty-three years; Mr. Tolles died in 2008 at the age of 85. In 1965, the busy mother of six was sidelined by a back injury. With time on her hands, Martha Tolles turned to writing children's fiction and saw her first novel, entitled "Too Many Boys"(a nod to the fact that of her six children, she had only one daughter) which would later be named"Katie and Those Boys."
Since then, Tolles has published more than a dozen titles, including "Who's Reading Darcie's Diary?" (1985), "Katie for President" (1988), and "Marrying Off Mom" (1990). A member of the Authors Guild and the Society of Children's Book Writers and Illustrators and twice a recipient of the Children's Choice Book List Award, Tolles'fiction continues to delight young readers with more than 2.3 million copies sold to date.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
Scope and Contents
The majority of this colleciton consists of manuscripts of Tolles' published and unpublished works, mostly typescripts with handwritten annotations. There are also some financial and legal documentation from the publishers such as invoices and contracts, as well as final published versions of the works.
The largest remainder of the collection is correspondence between Tolles and her editors, rejection letters from editors, and fan mail. Most of the fan mail was from children, and the collection includes a photograph album of pictures of themselves that the child fans sent to Tolles. There is also a small amount of publicity materials and articles about Tolles' work, as well as recordings of interviews with Tolles.
Children's literature -- Authorship; Children's literature, American -- History -- Sources; Tolles, Martha; Awards; Biographical sketches; Books; DVD video discs; Audiotapes; Videotapes; clippings; Galley proofs; Interviews; Contracts; notebooks; Notes; Publicity; Reviews; scrapbooks; photograph albums; CDs; Tolles, Martha
- Manuscripts, notebooks, rejection letters, and editor's letters, 1986-2013 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
- News articles, promotional materials and interviews, approximately 1991-2015 (Box 1)
- 3 VHS tapes: "Martha Tolles 11/1991," "Martha Tolles 5/15/89 Chadwick School," and "Martha's interview", approximately 1989-1991 (Box 1)
- 2 audio CDs: "An Oral History with Martha Tolles," El Toro Marine Corps Air Station Oral History Project – ©2012 Center for Oral and Public History, California State University, Fullerton (Box 1)
- DVD: "All Firm Sherry Sip Featuring Martha Tolles," Munger Tolles & Olson LLP, 2015 July 15 (Box 1)
- "Marrying Off Mom" manuscripts, approximately 1980s (Box 2)
- "Katie" books: notes, manuscripts, contracts, approximately 1960s-1980s (Box 2)
- Publicity and fan letters, approximately 1980s (Box 2)
- "Darci" series contracts and drafts, approximately 1980s (Box 2)
- Awards, approximately 1980s (Box 2)
- Books by Martha Tolles, approximately 1960s-1980s (Box 3)
- "Darci" books: notes, manuscripts, approximately 1980s (Box 3)
- "Marrying Off Mom" contracts, reviews, and drafts, 1989-1991 (Box 3)
- "Katie's Babysitting Job" contracts and drafts, approximately 1980s (Box 3)
- "Too Many Boys," multiple drafts, approximately 1960s (Box 3)
- Correspondence with editors, fan letters, and biographical information, approximately 1980s-1990s (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks and photograph albums, approximately 1980s-1990s (Box 3)
- Books by Martha Tolles, 1965-1990 (Box 3)
- Newspaper clippings and photograph album, approximately 1960s-1990s (Box 4)